Hello English Learners and welcome
back to English Pod. My name is Marco.
And my name is Catherine
and today we're talking about
money, but this time we're
talking about borrowing money.
Right, so we're
asking for money.
We're going to the bank
and we are asking for a loan.
But before we go, why don't we
take a look at vocabulary preview?
Very Cavalry preview.
Okay, so a loan is some
money that you get from the
banks that we're talking
about requesting a loan today.
All right, so you request for
a loan or you ask for a loan?
Exactly. So to request is to ask.
Okay, very good. And that's the word
that we have for vocabulary preview.
So let's listen to the
dialogue for the first time.
Hello, sir. May I help you?
Yes, I would like some
information for requesting a loan.
Very well. Here are the general
terms of our loan policies.
We pride ourselves
in having the lowest
interest rate in the
country for personal loans.
I see. So let me get this straight.
If I borrow, let's say, $10,000, how
much will I have to pay each month?
It depends on how long
you take to pay it back.
If we lend you $10,000 at an annual
interest rate of 10% for 48 months,
you would have to pay each month a portion
of the loan, which is called the principle,
and another small portion
of the annual interest rate.
This, of course, is considering
that you don't default on a payment.
It sounds good, but there's just one
problem. I have a terrible credit score.
That is a very serious problem,
you see. The bank must
assess your personal
information, past loans, assets,
and any other relevant
information, such as
your credit score in
order to approve your loan.
You know what? I don't really
need the money. Thanks, anyways.
All right, we're back. So now
why don't we take a look at
some of the key words that
we'll find in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
All right, so on language takeaway
today, we have a couple of different words.
Why don't we start off
with the loan policies?
Okay, so a policy is like a rule.
For example, a government
can have policies, but in this case,
the loan policy is the rules
regarding the loan that you have.
Right, so maybe the loan policies
could include what's the maximum
length of your loan, or maybe
what's the annual interest rate, etc.?
How much you have to pay each month?
Exactly.
So loan policy is the rules related
to the loan that you've taken out.
And we have some very, very important
words following this, and they go together.
So the first word is to borrow.
Okay, so you probably know
this word already to borrow.
So can I borrow your pen?
Can I borrow some money?
Sure. Let me give you my pen.
Let me give you my money.
Okay, but wait, giving is different because
giving means I don't have to get it back.
Right. So if you want to give
it to someone temporarily,
then you lend them your pen
or you lend them some money.
Great. So to borrow is to
take something from someone
knowing that you will
have to give it back later.
And to lend is to give
it to someone, right?
So can you lend me your pen?
That means can you give it to me please.
Right. And this is a common mistake
with language learners, especially
English learners, that they make the
mistake of using borrow instead of lend.
So can you borrow me some money? Right.
So can you lend me some money? Sure,
but I expect you to pay me back later.
Okay, very good. And if I pay you
back later, I'll include an interest rate.
Will you really? No, no, not really.
Mostly it's banks that
ask for an interest rate.
So in this case, an interest rate
means the amount of money that
a bank will charge you in addition
to the money that you owe them.
Exactly. So it's called an interest rate
and it's a rate because it's a percentage.
Five percent. Exactly. Five, ten percent.
That is an interest rate.
And now moving on, if you
have a loan and you have to pay
each month, be careful to
not default on your payments.
Okay, default in the banking world,
this means to not be able to pay your loan.
So that means that if I owe
$1,000 to you, Bank of Marco, and
I don't have the money, I
can't pay for it, then I default.
So to be late or to not make the payment.
It's a verb to default. Very good.
And will the person
asking for the loan has a
small problem, his credit
score is not very good.
Okay, I think he calls it
terrible. And one of the ways that
you get a terrible credit
score is by defaulting on a loan.
But it also means that maybe
you borrow money or you
have credit cards and
you can't pay off your bills.
And so a credit score is
very important in America
and it's like a report
card for your finances.
Right. So for example, if your credit
score is a report card and you have an A
credit score, that means that the banks
won't have a problem with lending you money.
Or if you want to buy
a new car, it'll be okay.
But if you don't pay your bills on time
or you default on your loans, then maybe
you'll have a C or a D and then people will
not really lend you money in the future.
They won't trust you. Exactly.
All right. So that's credit score.
That's all the words we
have for fluency builder.
Why don't we listen to the dialogue
again and we'll be back shortly.
Hello, sir. May I help you?
Yes. I would like some
information for requesting a loan.
Very well. Here are the general
terms of our loan policies.
We pride ourselves
in having the lowest
interest rate in the
country for personal loans.
I see. So let me get this
straight. If I borrow, let's
say $10,000, how much will
I have to pay each month?
It depends on how long you take to pay it
back. If we lend you $10,000 at an annual
interest rate of 10% for 48 months, you would
have to pay each month a portion of the loan,
which is called the principle and another
small portion of the annual interest rate.
This, of course, is considering
that you don't default on a payment.
It sounds good, but there's just one
problem. I have a terrible credit score.
That is a very serious problem, you
see. The bank must assess your personal
information, past loans, assets,
and any other relevant information,
such as your credit score in
order to approve your loan.
You know what? I don't
really need the money.
Thanks, anyways.
All right, we're back.
So now what do we take
a look at three key
phrases on fluency builder?
Fluency builder.
Let me get this straight. We're going
to do fluency builder. That's right.
Wait, I don't. Wait.
Okay, so this is our first
phrase, let me get this straight.
And this is a fixed phrase that
means we always say it the same way.
Wait, let me get this straight.
We always say it the same way.
Right. So you're asking for a
confirmation or you're repeating
what that person said, just
to be sure that it's correct.
Exactly. So maybe you don't
understand something or maybe
you think you might have
misunderstood. You say, hey,
so let me get this straight and
you repeat what the person just said.
It's a way for you to, like you say,
get confirmation on what you've heard.
Very good. Let me get this
straight. And now moving on,
we have the phrase, pay it
back. You have to pay it back.
Okay. And so in this case,
we have the verb to pay, but
we also have the word back.
So pay it back means to repay.
So if we take out a loan, we obviously
have to pay it back to the bank.
So you have to pay the loan back.
Okay. So just remember that these
words often go together to pay
it back. I'll pay you back, I promise.
Can you lend me a dollar
or pay it back tomorrow?
I don't worry about it. All right.
And the bank started off saying,
we pride ourselves in having the
lowest interest rate in the country.
Yeah, right. All right.
So we pride ourselves.
What does it mean if I, if I
pride myself in something?
The word pride means
to be really happy
about something that
has to do with yourself.
So something that you're
proud of is something
that you want to tell a
lot of other people about.
So for example, a father
may say, my son just got
straight A's and he's an
excellent soccer player.
And so he's proud of his
son, but to be to pride oneself
means to be really happy with
the way that you do something.
So for example, if I've
never smoked, right, so
I can say, I pride myself
in being a non smoker.
Or I could say, I pride
myself in always saving
lots of money for my
paycheck. Very good.
So it means I try to do this because I
know it's a good thing, but you feel very
good about this and you feel that, you
know, people should be proud of you as well.
So we could ask our
students here, what do you
pride yourselves in as a
challenge for the website?
Alright, so why don't we listen to the
dialogue for the last time and we'll be back.
Hello, sir. May I help you?
Yes, I would like some
information for requesting a loan.
Very well. Here are the general
terms of our loan policies.
We pride ourselves
in having the lowest
interest rate in the
country for personal loans.
I see. So let me get this
straight. If I borrow, let's
say, $10,000, how much will
I have to pay each month?
It depends on how long you take to pay it back. If we lend you
$10,000 at an annual interest rate of 10% for 48 months, you would
have to pay each month a portion of the loan, which is called the
principal, and another small portion of the annual interest rate.
This, of course, is considering
that you don't default on a payment.
It sounds good, but there's just one
problem. I have a terrible credit score.
That is a very serious problem, you see. The bank
must assess your personal information, past loans,
assets, and any other relevant information, such
as your credit score in order to approve your loan.
You know what? I don't really
need the money. Thanks anyways.
All right, very good.
So as you say, saving is
important, and sometimes
do you think you need a loan?
I think sometimes people need loans because
they want to go into business, for example.
So people who want to
go into small businesses
are open their own
companies need startup capital.
And so this is a really great example
of when people don't have money
lying around and will go to find
a bank that will give them a loan.
So yeah, I think it's really important, especially for the economy
of a country, for business loans or small business loans to
be available because sometimes it's very difficult to find a
bank that will actually lend a person money to start a business.
Usually they won't have a problem
with lending the money to buy a
new car, but to start off a
business, it's completely the opposite.
It is, and one of the really popular trends in foreign investment right now is
called micro lending. So micro loans, and that means that if I want to help people in
a very poor country, I can lend $100 for someone to buy a sewing machine, or for
someone to buy a small computer, $500 for a small computer, and that is a micro loan.
It's a very, very small loan
from one thing, and that can
help them towards their goal
of being a business person.
Right, and you're not really
getting money out of it, though.
You're not charging
like 100% interest rate.
You're not, you're charging like one or two
percent interest, very low interest, and
you're giving people a chance to pay the
money back because it's such a small amount.
Wow, that's really good, a really positive
thing. Very good, so if you have any questions,
any comments or any suggestions, please
come to our website at www.EnglishPod.
com and we'll see you guys
there. Bye, everyone. Bye.